hi everyone this is so big league this
year I can't believe it we have like
this team of people in the back helping
there's real chairs and look how many
seats there are this is so exciting
I'm Jessica Livingston I'm one of the
founders of Y Combinator and it's been
more than seven years since we started
YC and in that time we've funded four
hundred and sixty-seven startups so I've
seen a lot of patterns Thank You us I
was a little nervous back there so
thanks there's a talk I always want to
give at the beginning of each batch
warning everyone about stuff that I know
is probably gonna happen to them I
finally wrote down my thoughts and I'm
gonna share it with you today so we all
know that lots of smart and talented
people start startups on the left side
there you see huge numbers of startups
getting started and yet if you look at
the other side a few years later there's
actually only a handful of startups that
are big successes what's happening in
the middle there that's causing such
failure it's like there's a tunnel full
of monsters that kill them along the way
and I just want to thank minnow monsters
for providing me these fabulous cartoon
monsters so I'm going to tell you about
these monsters today so you can know how
to avoid them in general your best
weapon against these monsters is
determination and even though we usually
use one word for it
determination is really two separate
things its resilience and Drive
resilience keeps you from being pushed
backwards and drive makes you go
forwards one reason you need resilience
in a start-up is that you're gonna get
rejected a lot even the most famous
startups had a surprising amount of
rejection early on everyone you
encounter will have doubts about what
you're doing whether its investors
potential employees reporters your
family and friends what you don't
you lies until you start a start-up is
how much external validation you've
gotten for the conservative choices
you've made in the past you go to
college and everyone says great you
graduate and get a job at Google and
everyone says great well what do you
think happens when you quit your job to
start a company to rent out air beds
this is Airbnb x' website when they
first launched in 2007
I mean look up there where they explain
what they do it says to designers create
a new way to connect at the IDSA
conference I've never even heard of that
conference and over on the left it says
list your air bed it was only for air
beds I mean it's unbelievable this is
not the sort of thing that you get a lot
of external validation for almost
everyone is more impressed when you get
a job at Google then if you make a
website for people to rent out air beds
for conferences and yet this is one of
the most successful startups so even if
your air B&B you're gonna start out
looking like an egg blue Ugly Duckling
to most people here the air B&B founders
when they did YC back in early 2009 and
at this point they'd already endured
tons of rejection you should check out
Brian's talk from the 2010 startup
school it's a very inspirational story
but by the time they came to us they had
maxed out their credit cards they were
eating leftover Cap'n McCain cereal they
were at the end of their rope and
everyone thought their idea was crazy
even I actually did but they knew they
were on to something
and during YC they made some key changes
to their site they talked to users they
set their goals and they measured
everything and the graph started to go
up remember the new ideas usually seemed
crazy at first but if you have a good
idea and you execute well everyone will
see it eventually we funded Eric magic
offski about two years ago when he was
working on impulse the predecessor to
the Pebble watch
Eric was a single founder and these
watches there have something in common
the terrifies investors their hardware
poor Eric had a really hard time getting
funding no one wanted to fund the
hardware company he met with more than
like 30 investors who all said things
like I love the idea but I can't fund a
hardware company some claim they just
didn't fund hardware companies as a rule
others said that there are too many
capital expenses up front they all said
no when he showed them the concept but
he'd been building the pebble based on
all this user feedback from the impulse
and he felt strongly that people wanted
this product so I remember he talked to
Paul and they agreed he should just give
up investors and put it on Kickstarter
his original goal was to raise a hundred
thousand dollars to make a thousand
watches and instead of a hundred
thousand dollars pebble raised ten point
two million dollars in 30 days the
largest amount of money ever raised on
Kickstarter even Y Combinator got
rejected when we first started this here
is our first batch sitting at dinner in
Cambridge Massachusetts back in O five
now there are lots of organizations
doing what we do but trust me when we
first started people thought we were
crazy or just stupid even our own
lawyers tried to talk us out of it but
eight teams of founders took a chance on
Y Combinator and moved to Cambridge and
got there twelve thousand dollars per
team and I think they tell you they had
a really great experience we too knew we
were on to something interesting so we
focused on making something that a few
people loved and we just expanded slowly
from there but it was a slow process
when we came out to Silicon Valley in
the winter of oh-6 we hardly knew anyone
so we decided we'd focus on meeting new
investors to convince them to come to
demo day
I got an introduction to the number one
angel investor in the valley Ron Conway
and let me show you how he tried to
brush us off so we get the introduction
and Ron says is this in Boston I stick
to local and I said no we're in Mountain
View and we'd love to have you come to
demo day and he said so is this a chance
to invest in your incubator and I
replied no we're not asking you to
invest in us we were asking you to
invest in the individual startups and he
said off to circle back to you I'm
jammed up we got the jammed up right now
from Ron Conway was so embarrassing oh
my gosh but it all worked out in the end
here's Ron a year later speaking to the
winter o7 batch of founders he did wind
up coming to demo day and he was
impressed with what he saw
remember if you execute well eventually
you'll win people over and by the way I
should also point out that there's David
Rees anko who's speaking later today and
there's hard to gar who's now a partner
at YC it was their batch remember there
were two components to determination
resilience and drive we've talked about
why you need resilience because everyone
will be down on you but you need Drive
to overcome the sheer variety of
problems you'll face in a startup some
of them are painfully specific like a
lawsuit or a deal blowing up and some
are demoralizing ly vague like no one's
visiting your site and you can't figure
out why there's no playbook you can
consult when these problems come up you
have to improvise and sometimes you have
to do things that seem kind of abnormal
this is a picture of Rajat Suri he's the
founder of Elah cart yulik heart let's
restaurant customers order and pay
through a tablet he was a grad student
at MIT when he started the company and
he was so committed that he got a job as
a waiter to learn what restaurants were
like you see that air duct up there over
his head that looks like a halo this is
an exam
of a good founder here are the calls and
brothers who founded stripe Patrick
speaking right after me today actually
they do payment processing online when
these guys got started they were a pair
of young programmers they had no idea
how to make deals with banks and credit
card companies so I asked Patrick how
did you even convince these big
companies to work with you and one trick
he told me that worked was he started
with a phone call and then people would
pay attention to their arguments without
being distracted by their youth and by
the time they met in person and the
companies could tell how young they are
they were already impressed we funded
the lockitron guys back in the summer of
oh nine that's them actually at their YC
interview a year after YC they were
still figuring out their idea they lived
with the we pay guys and one day the we
pays were having a party for their
investors and by that point the
lockitron x' were working on a product
to lock your door with the iPhone they
were able to impress one of the
investors with their prototype and he
asked to have 40 installed at some
start-up offices he owned the founders
were totally psyched but the commercial
locks they needed to use cost 500 bucks
a pop they didn't have $20,000 to
fulfill that order so they went around
to local locksmiths and scrapyards
buying broken locks for 10 bucks apiece
they fixed them themselves and were able
to deliver on that order fast forward a
few years later and these guys were
ready to launch the newest version of
the lockitron and they decided to go on
Kickstarter and guess what a day after
lockitron submitted their campaign
Kickstarter changed their policy about
hardware companies and rejected them but
the lockitron guys decided to build
their own Kickstarter and they did it in
less than a week they wondered if anyone
would even come and not only did people
come but they've already sold close to
two million dollars worth of lockitron
x' that way so let me give you just one
last example
oops
ah there we go of improvising these are
the justin.tv founders when they first
got started and they were having a lot
of scaling issues and one weekend their
whole video system went down Kyle was in
charge of it but no one knew where Kyle
was and Kyle wasn't picking up his cell
phone this was live video so it was
pretty critical that this get fixed
immediately
so Michael Seibel called Kyle's friends
and found out that he was in late Lake
Tahoe and got the address so here's a
problem for you you know the address of
where someone is and he's not answering
his phone
how do you get a message to him
immediately Michael went onto Yelp and
looked for a pizza place near the house
and called them up and said I want to
have a pizza delivered but never mind
about the pizza just send the delivery
guy over and say these four words the
site is down
so the pizza place was like really
confused by this and they send the pizza
guy without a pizza kyle answers the
door the delivery guys like the site is
down Kyle's like oh no and he fixed the
site it was down for less than one hour
from start to finish all right so now
we're gonna move on to another monster
co-founder disputes I think people
underestimate how critical founder
relationships are to the success of a
startup
unfortunately I've seen more founder
breakups than I care to even count and
when it happens it can crush a startup
be very careful when you decide to start
a startup with someone do you know them
well have you worked with them or gone
to school with them don't just slap
yourself together with someone just
because they're available and seem good
enough you'll probably regret it and if
you start seeing red flags do something
about it
don't think it'll just go away it's a
red flag when you find yourself worrying
whether your co-founders trustworthy or
whether he or she works hard enough or
as competent when founders break up for
whatever reason it's a blow to the
startups productivity and morale if
there's three in one leaves it's not so
bad but if there's two and one leaves
it's hard because now you're a single
founder now we come to the investor
monster investors tend to have a herd
mentality they like you if other
investors like you so if no one likes
you until others do what happens when
you talk to the first ones no one likes
you it's like the catch-22 of not being
able to get a job because you don't have
enough experience you're except you're
really starting off in a hole and you
have to work your way out of it you have
to meet with lots of investors and hear
things like I'd be interested once you
get some more traction or who else is
investing if you work hard enough you
may be able to find a few people who are
excited enough about you and the idea to
fund you even though you don't have
other investors yet then when you have a
few investors you can start to make the
herd
tality work for you instead of against
you fundraising is hard and slow until
it's fast and easy but working to
convince those first few investors can
be really demoralizing it's a grind
investors also like to drag their feet
left to their own devices they'll just
keep delaying there's no downside for
them to delay
whereas delay will kill you because
while you're fundraising
your company will grind to a halt and by
the way there are some really good
investors who aren't like this I'm just
talking about the the median investor
but it blows my mind how many successful
startups had a hard time fundraising at
first if you remember one piece of
advice about investors it's that you've
got to create some type of competitive
situation I'll give you what is always
stuck in my mind is the most amazing
example of this one of the founders of
one of our more successful startups had
a long-standing relationship with a VC
so when the founder started the company
and did YC this VC kept in touch for the
three months not really doing anything
except kind of keeping a benevolent eye
on the founder the VC attended demo day
but didn't invest after a few months the
startup gets a term sheet from a
prestigious VC and for those of you in
the audience who don't know a term sheet
is an offer to invest in your company
when the vers VC heard about this he
shifted into panic mode he faxed the
founder a term sheet from his firm with
the valuation blank and just said fill
in whatever valuation you want and we're
in
and there are worse things investors can
do than just delay sometimes they say
yes and then change their mind it's not
a deal until the money is in the bank
and we've seen some founders learn that
the hard way I could tell you a lot of
horror stories to frighten you but just
remember that fundraising is a bitch why
see founders raise money under really
good circumstances and even for them
it's a bitch sorry to swear one of the
reasons fundraising can be so damaging
to your company is that it's a
distraction we warn everyone
early on it YC that there's you know you
need to be very careful about
distractions and no one's stupid enough
to play video games all day but the kind
of distractions founders fall for are
things that seem like a reasonable way
to spend their time we tell people that
during YC there's three things that they
should be focusing on writing code
talking to users and exercising and
maybe that's a little bit extreme but
the point is early on nothing else for
your startup matters you need to figure
out how to make something people want
and do it well
don't spend all your time networking
don't hire an army of interns just build
stuff and talk to users and by the way
fundraising is a distraction but it's a
necessary one so just try to spend as
little time on it as possible
one thing that isn't necessary and is a
bad distraction is talking to corporate
development people or Corp dev these are
people at big companies who buy startups
so you get a call from a Corp dev person
and they want to learn more about what
you're doing and explore possible ways
of working together the founder thinks
oh boy this important company wants to
work with me I should at least take the
meeting and I hate to sound harsh but
what these meetings are really for is a
way for them to see if they want to do
an HR acquisition and an HR acquisition
means they're essentially trying to hire
you and there's such a dangerous
distraction that I've given them their
own
monster there's nothing wrong with HR
acquisitions if that's what you want to
do but most founders don't start
startups just to get a job at a big
company for what essentially is a nice
hiring bonus talking to corporate have
people early on isn't just a waste of
time it's uniquely demoralizing and I
see the cycle happen over and over the
founders go to meet with the Corp dev
people and think the meeting was great
they're so friendly and enthusiastic and
the founders delude themselves into
thinking that their startup is going to
be the one that gets bought for ten
million dollars after only five months
they start to think okay yeah we'd kind
of like to get acquired and they start
to not work on their startup anymore and
they lose momentum then they get the
offer and it's essentially what they
would have gotten if they'd walked in
off the street and gotten a job but by
then they've gotten so accustomed to the
idea of selling that they take it so
going down the Corp dev road seriously
can deflate your ambitions okay now we
come to the fiercest monster of all the
difficulty of making something people
want it's so hard that most startups
aren't able to do it you're trying to
figure out something that's never been
done before not making something people
want is the biggest cause of failure we
see early on with the second biggest
being founder disputes in order to make
something people want being brilliant
and determined is not enough you have to
be able to talk to your users and adjust
your idea accordingly and ordinarily you
have to change your idea quite a lot
even if you start out with a reasonably
good one
remember this website air
bed-and-breakfast was a rather narrower
idea when they first launched they
started out as a site that let people
rent out air beds to travelers for
conferences then they changed to renting
out air beds then they change to renting
out a room or a couch but the hosts had
to be there to make breakfast then they
finally realized that there was all this
pent-up demand to rent out entire places
this evolution shows that you may begin
with kind of a general vision of what
your startup is doing but you often have
to try several different approaches to
get it right and sometimes you have to
totally change your idea order ahead
which lets you order takeout on your
cellphone was the founders sixth idea we
funded them for the first thing I think
they presented on demo day with the
third and it wasn't until order ahead
that they hit on their big idea even if
you don't need to change the overall
idea much you still tend to have to do
lots of refinement and one of the best
examples of this is Dropbox here's a
photo of drew Houston during YC in the
summer of a 7 he and Arash were working
on something that was obviously
necessary but the reason it was hard to
predict early on whether they'd succeed
is that there were lots of people doing
this the way to win in this world was to
execute well and it didn't happen
overnight
they had to get a thousand and one
details right there were a lot of
unglamorous schleps between that
photograph and this one looks good
between starting the company and being
on the cover of Forbes you're gonna have
some dramatic ups and downs in a startup
you don't have the damping that you'd
have as part of a larger organization
circumstances just kind of fling you
about the process is often described as
a roller coaster because you're up one
minute and down the next lots of
rollercoaster stories that I know
involve fundraising and one of the most
extreme ones happened to some people we
funded in their previous startup it was
based in Houston and they got a term
sheet from a top-tier VC in Silicon
Valley and one of the conditions was
that they base their company in the
valley
so they said fine they sold their houses
they they moved their families into
corporate housing in Houston until they
found places in the valley the documents
were already signed and the money was
scheduled to be wired on Friday and
we're gonna start working on Monday out
of the VCS office so Friday comes around
and for some reason the money was not
wired so they call the VC to ask if they
should still come out and the VC is like
absolutely so they get into their
minivan and they drive from Houston to
Silicon Valley and they stop in Vegas to
celebrate this is the up part of the
rollercoaster so on Monday they set up
all their stuff in the conference room
of the VC fund all six of their team
there and by that Wednesday the money
was still not wired so they had a bored
weaning plan for that day and they
decide to invite the VC and in this
meeting the CEO talked about how sign up
numbers had gone down temporarily
because they had changed the way they
measured them I think you know how this
story is gonna turn out the VC had
actually gotten buyer's remorse and he
used this as an excuse to break the deal
remember they had signed all the
documents sold their homes moved to
Silicon Valley and we're just waiting to
get the seven million dollars wired to
them and instead the VC bails he kicks
them out of their conference room the
founders had to call their wives back in
Houston and go back with their tails
between their legs and they had delay
everyone off can you imagine just a few
days before they were celebrating in
Vegas and now they have nothing
incidentally to get to a story this
extreme we had to use an example of a
startup we didn't find fun cuz I don't
think a VC would probably do this to a
startup we funded now let me just tell
you about the other half of the
rollercoaster we funded the codecademy
team in the summer of 2011 their
original idea didn't work and they kept
exploring new ones
it wasn't until late July that they
started working on their idea for
teaching people to code online they
launched just three days before demo day
and in those three days they got over
200,000 users I mean they only launched
so they could get up on demo day and say
that they were a launch company that
Zach Sims they're presenting on demo day
they never expected that in just three
days
they could go from a start up with a nun
launched idea and get up on stage and
announce they had two hundred thousand
users which is just about the most
exciting thing you can say to investors
the theme here is how extreme things can
be just remember that no extreme ever
lasts don't let yourself get immobilized
by sadness when things go wrong just
keep putting one foot in front of the
other and no will get better but don't
get complacent when things are going
well in reality things are never as bad
or as good as they seem and by the way
what makes this roller coaster even
worse is that while you're on it there's
this huge audience watching everything
you do you'll have trolls and reporters
say outrageous things about you online
so be ready for that and have a thick
skin so everyone knows that startups are
hard yet when we watch people do them
they're always surprised the reason
they're surprised is that they don't
realize how bad these specific problems
can be I've seen some very smart and
talented people get so demoralized that
they just gave up startups are not for
the faint of heart and I realize that
this is not new news but I wanted you to
at least understand how they're hard
early on so that when you run into these
specific monsters you'll know what to do
thank you